We have gotten an introduction to stored
procedures and specifically the input and
output parameters, but we discovered that
output does not appear in a query window.
Output information is used in an app instead.
If we want to actually see the results from
the query that run inside a stored procedure,
we need to include, in the stored procedure a
RETURN function. This is a stored procedure, it
is similar to the one with the input and output
parameters as the SELECT statement goes through
and gets to DepartmentID for each employee, WHERE
the BusinessEntityID matches with whatever the
input is through the input parameter EmployeeID,
which is declared before the query used in this
stored procedure starts to run. This makes sense,
in that we need to know what is in the
parameter before it can be used as criteria.
After the SELECT statement notice the
RETURN word, this returns the information
found in the query to the query window. I
will run the CREATE PROCEDURE statement,
and then run the execute statement to see the
Department history for Employee number 16.
It turns out that the employee has been in
two departments. Before we leave this topic
you may wonder why this line is commented out to
begin with. For some stored procedure statements,
no other statements are allowed in the same
window. Now importantly, some stored procedures
actually change data. We want to make sure a
CREATE PROCEDURE statement can be run before
we execute a line using a stored procedure.
Again, one main purpose of a stored procedure
is to hide its code from code written within
an app and not have SELECT statements, which
expose database objects, shown within code for a
console app, desktop app, mobile app, or web app.